<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Nlp on About me</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/nlp/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Nlp on About me</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.140.1</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Apr 2025 10:30:58 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/nlp/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Understanding approximate nearest neighbor algorithm</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2025-04-19-ann/ann/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Apr 2025 10:30:58 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2025-04-19-ann/ann/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is about the approximate nearest neighbor (ANN) algorithm. The code for this post is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/code/steffenhaeussler/understanding-approx-nearest-neighbor-algorithm&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, where I provide an example of using a framework and a python implementation. Most python implementation were written with the help of a LLM. I&amp;rsquo;m amazed, how helpful they are for learning new things. I see them like a drunken professor, which with the right approach will be a very helpful tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a next step in understanding RAGs, I want to have a closer look at approximate nearest neighbor algorithms. Basically, the purpose is to find the closest vector to a query vector in a database. Since I&amp;rsquo;m also interested into the implementation, I follow mostly this amazing blog post. Vector search is the basic component of vector databases and their main purpose. ANN algorithms are looking for a close match instead of an exact match. This loss of accuracy allows an improvement of efficieny, which allows the search through much bigger datasets, high-dimensional data and real-time apllications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Short example of Information Retrieval</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2025-03-10-retrieval/retrieval/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 10:30:58 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2025-03-10-retrieval/retrieval/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some time ago, I did a small project on information retrieval. I think, it\s a good idea to share it with all its shortcomings.
Here is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/code/steffenhaeussler/examples-for-information-retrieval&#34;&gt;code&lt;/a&gt;. Sadly, the LLM part doesn&amp;rsquo;t work with the quantized model, so I commented it out.
The project is a small information retrieval of a FAQ, where I want to map the correct answer to a question. In my example, it&amp;rsquo;s a 1:1 mapping between question and answer, but it also works with multiple answers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Overview of RAG (Retrieval-Augmented Generation) systems</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-12-27-overview/rag_overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2024 10:30:58 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-12-27-overview/rag_overview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s been a while since my last post, mostly because of my own laziness. Over the past year, I’ve been working on several projects, one of which is a small RAG (Retrieval-Augmented Generation) system. I implemented it to combine external knowledge (in this case internal safety documents) with a large language model (LLM). This approach allows the use of data that the LLM wasn&amp;rsquo;t trained on and also helps reduce hallucinations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Training a language model from scratch</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-04-21-training/llm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2023 10:30:58 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2023-04-21-training/llm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is a short overview over a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/code/steffenhaeussler/train-a-language-model-from-scratch/notebook&#34;&gt;work project&lt;/a&gt;, where I trained a language model for invoices. This so-called base model is then fine-tuned for text classification on customer data. Due to data privacy, a non-disclosure agreement, ISO 27001 and SOAP2, I&amp;rsquo;m not allowed to publish any results. Believe me, it works like 🚀✨🪐.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A language model is trained on large amounts of textual data to understand the patterns and structure of language. The primary goal of a language model is to predict the probability of the next word or sequence of words in a sentence given the previous words.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
