<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>engineering on About me</title>
    <link>https://steffenhaeussler.github.io/tags/engineering/</link>
    <description>Recent content in engineering on About me</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2023 10:30:50 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://steffenhaeussler.github.io/tags/engineering/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Endpoint validation</title>
      <link>https://steffenhaeussler.github.io/posts/pydantic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2023 10:30:50 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://steffenhaeussler.github.io/posts/pydantic/</guid>
      <description>Hi,
In my previous job, I spent hours debugging internal data transformations to figure out the received data from an external API was faulty. This issue would not appeared with schema validation. My fault was that I trusted the incoming data and didn’t check for data consistency. Learning from mistakes and saving time, I would set up a small example for JSON validation via Pydantic. FastAPI relies heavily on pydantic and I use it for validating the incoming request and outgoing response.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fast data transfer to or from s3</title>
      <link>https://steffenhaeussler.github.io/posts/s3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 10:30:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://steffenhaeussler.github.io/posts/s3/</guid>
      <description>Hi,
This post is an homage to a stackoverflow post copying data from s3. This shared work saved me a lot of time. I believe that individuals who share their work do not receive sufficient recognition.
The problem is that I have multiple Gb of data separated into thousands of files. Those files are selected for download by the semi-automated pipeline for model training. So the number of files to download varies from pipeline run to pipeline run.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The importance of building things by yourself</title>
      <link>https://steffenhaeussler.github.io/posts/first/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 23:30:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://steffenhaeussler.github.io/posts/first/</guid>
      <description>Hi,
In this initial post, I want to draft the development of my FastAPI skeleton.
At the beginning of my career as a Data Scientist, I ran into the typical problem of model deployment to production. In a team of two scientists, I had the chance to write a micro-service with Flask from scratch out of necessity.
My first service followed strongly the example of Miguel Grinbergs great tutorial. The reason was simple, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t write proper code at this time.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
