<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>explainability on About me</title>
    <link>https://steffenhaeussler.github.io/tags/explainability/</link>
    <description>Recent content in explainability on About me</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Dec 2023 10:30:58 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://steffenhaeussler.github.io/tags/explainability/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning model explainability</title>
      <link>https://steffenhaeussler.github.io/posts/dl_model_explainability/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Dec 2023 10:30:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://steffenhaeussler.github.io/posts/dl_model_explainability/</guid>
      <description>Hi,
In my first post, I looked into the explainability of classical machine learning models. As a next step, I&amp;rsquo;m interested in the explainability of neural networks. Model explainability is easy for simple models (linear regression, decision trees), and some tools exist for more complex algorithms (ensemble trees). Therefore, I highly recommend the book Interpretable Machine Learning by Christoph Molnar for a deeper theoretical understanding. All different approaches for model explanability are shown with a PyTorch model in this kaggle notebook.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Model explainability</title>
      <link>https://steffenhaeussler.github.io/posts/model_explainability/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 10:30:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://steffenhaeussler.github.io/posts/model_explainability/</guid>
      <description>Hi,
Some months have passed since my last post. Model explainability is easy for simple models (linear regression, decision trees), and some tools exist for more complex algorithms (ensemble trees). I want to dig into the tools to interpret more complex models with this post. Therefore, I highly recommend the book Interpretable Machine Learning by Christoph Molnar for a deeper theoretical understanding. All different approaches for model explanability are shown with a RandomForest model in this kaggle notebook.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
